Guide to the Grace Cavalieri papers, 1945-2022 MS2007
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Grace Cavalieri papers
1945-2022
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Cavalieri, Grace
MS2007
89 Linear Feet
Collection contains audio cassettes, CD-ROMs, literary journals, anthologies, plays, video cassettes, and magnetic audiotape reels. These electronic audio and video recordings produced between 1976 and 2000s. The audio recordings are of famous primarily local poets that Grace Cavalieri interviewed on her radio program The Poet and the Poem and an earlier radio show titled Poetry from the City. These shows date from the middle 1970s through the present.
Acquisition Information
Donated in two large accessions 1989 and 2007. Smaller accessions arrive a few times per year.
Collection Organization
Organized into sixteen series: Magnetic audiotape reels, Videotape cassette, Audiotape cassettes, Published works, Writing, production and publicity, Compact discs, Long-playing record, DVDs, Digital audiotapes, Correspondence, Collaborative works, Poet and the Poem radio show supporting materials, Employment, Bunny and the Crocodile Press/Forest Woods Media Productions, Inc., Photographs and negatives, and Web Archives.
Historical or Biographical Note
Grace Cavalieri, an award winning poet and playwright, lived for 25 years in Washington D.C., and through her weekly radio program, "The Poet and the Poem," continues to be an important figure in the literary community of this city. She is the author of many books of poetry, including Why I Cannot Take a Lover (1975), Creature Comforts (1982), Bliss (1986), Trenton (1990), New and Selected Poems (1994), Migrations (1995), Pinecrest Rest Haven (1998), and What I Would Do For Love (2004). She has had twenty-one plays produced for stage and radio, including a successful dramatic version of Pinecrest Rest Haven, and an off- Broadway production of Getting Ready at the WPA Theater. She published a major anthology of Washington, D.C. Writers, The WPFW Writers Anthology, in 1992. Her drama, Quilting the Sun, enjoyed a staged reading by its NYC cast at the Smithsonian Institution. She has written texts and lyrics for opera, co-authoring two productions, "String of Pearls," and "Migrations," and has written three radio dramas that received national broadcast.
Cavalieri was one of the founders of the Washington Writers' Publishing House, and served on its editorial board from 1976 to 1986. She also runs her own small press and media production company, The Bunny and the Crocodile Press/Forest Woods Media Productions, Inc. She was an Associate Director of Programming at the Public Broadcasting System [PBS] for five years and then served as program officer of the media program at the National Endowment for the Humanities [NEH] from 1982 to 1988. She has lectured and taught throughout the country at several colleges and universities, and was, for 25 years, visiting poet at St. Mary's College of Maryland. She was resident writer at the Word Works annual retreat in Tuscany, 1996-2003.
Many of the sound recordings in this collection are related to the work Cavalieri has done with the radio station WPFW-FM. Cavalieri and a core staff opened this non-commercial radio station after being awarded a 3-year National Endowment for the Arts [NEA] Radio Development Grant in 1976. Cavalieri worked for the station as Director of Arts Programming from 1976 to 1978, and as a radio producer from 1976 to 1985. She has produced more than 100 programs in radio drama, and poetry and arts criticism including "Poetry from the City," "Expressions," and "Writer's Workshop on the Air."
Cavalieri worked as a radio broadcaster at WPFW-FM from 1977 to 1997, and is best known in the Washington literary community for her program "The Poet and the Poem." The show aired weekly from 1977 to 1997, and was distributed nationally through the Pacifica Radio station network, which includes KPFA-FM/KPFB-FM Berkeley, California, KPFK-FM North Hollywood, California, and KPFT-FM Houston, Texas. Cavalieri stopped airing "The Poet and the Poem" through WPFW-FM in 1997, and she now presents this series to public radio from the Library of Congress via NPR satellite. Approximately ten episodes from the Library of Congress series are produced each season, and podcasts are made available through the Library of Congress' website.
Typically, "The Poet and the Poem" features poets who live in the Washington, D.C. area and have become a part of the Washington literary community. Cavalieri has been committed to presenting various American cultural traditions on the program, and is particularly interested in the black literary community. The recordings of her programs include a significant collection of African-American poets.
She has received many awards including the Pen-Syndicated Fiction Award, the Allen Ginsberg Poetry Award, Bordighera Poetry Award, Paterson Poetry Prize, The Witter Bynner Foundation for Poetry, The National Endowment for the Arts, The Corporation for Public Broadcasting Silver Medal, The National Commission on Working Women, and The American Association of University Women. She has enjoyed several state arts and humanities council awards and fellowships. She received the inaugural Columbia Award from the Folger Shakespeare Library Poetry Committee for "significant contribution to poetry."
In 2019 Grace was named the Poet Laureate for the State of Maryland.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence; manuscripts and drafts of both published and unpublished literary works; notes and research materials; promotional and production-related material for Cavalieri's plays; items relating to Cavalieri's awards; documents pertaining to her lecturing and teaching careers; documents pertaining to her work for the Public Broadcasting System, the radio station WPFW-FM, and the Washington Writers' Publishing House; legal and financial documentation; newspaper and magazine clippings; serials that include poetry, essays, and reviews written by Cavalieri; collaborative work and manuscripts written by other individuals; audio and audio-visual recordings; original artwork; music manuscript and scores; and photographs, negatives, and slides. The collection materials date from 1945-2022 with bulk dates 1965-2018. These records are documents that Grace Cavalieri created, received, or collected throughout her career as a writer, educator, and producer.
The audio and audio-visual materials in this collection date from 1974 to 2011, and include multiple formats such as magnetic audiotape reels, audiotape cassettes, Digital Audiotape Cassettes, Compact Discs, CD-ROMs, videotape cassettes, DVDs, and an LP album. The videotapes and DVDs consist primarily of recordings of "On the Go with AAUW," a public access television program produced by the Alexandria, Virginia branch of the American Association of University Women. Recordings of poetry readings and award ceremonies are also present. The audiotapes, CDs, and CD-ROMs in this collection consist mainly of recordings of collaborative work by Cavalieri and musician Vivian Adelberg Rudow, as well as arts and literature-oriented radio programs which were produced by Grace Cavalieri for WPFW-FM from the late 1976 to 1997, and for the Library of Congress from 1997 to 2019 and now she produces them independently. These programs include "Poetry from the City," a program which aired live poetry readings given at various bookstores and libraries in the city, including some readings from E. Ethelbert Miller's well-known "Ascension Poetry Reading Series" which focuses on black and third world writers living in the United States; "Expressions," a program that featured literary critics discussing the works of selected poets; and "Writer's Workshop on the Air," a program for which writers could earn college credit by sending in their manuscripts and listening to the program while professional writers responded to their work on the air; and "The Poet and the Poem."
Recordings of, and supporting material for, Cavalieri's radio program "The Poet and the Poem" - the title of which she took from Judson Jerome's book of the same name on American poetry - comprise the largest part of this collection. Typically, the radio programs feature poets who are native to the Washington, D.C. area or have become a part of the Washington D.C. literary community. Included here are Poets Laureate of the United States Richard Wilbur, Howard Nemerov, Mark Strand, and Ted Kooser. Numerous important African-American writers are to be found in this collection, including Gwendolyn Brooks, Alice Walker, Rita Dove, May Miller, Billy Collins, June Jordan, Lucille Clifton, E. Ethelbert Miller, Audre Lorde and Kweli Smith. Additionally, several internationally known authors appear here, including Allen Ginsberg and Margaret Atwood. The recordings were on different AV carriers and thus are part of numerous series. In addition since 2016, Special Collections has been using Archive-It to capture the Poet and the Poem from the Library of Congress website and Grace's personal website. The links to this content is in Series 16 and available through the GW website.
The collaborative work in this collection includes original prints, illustrations, photographs, and slides by visual artist Mary Ellen Long, and music scores and music recordings by composer Vivian Adelberg Rudow.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for use. Please note: For series 3, in 2020 a set of the Poet and the Poem programs and well as some additional content in this series were digitized. Those files are not yet uploaded to the Internet due to licensing issues. Please contact Special Collections if you would like to listen to any recording.
Separated Materials
Often accessions to this collection include publications. If these publications are written by local poets or published by local presses they are retained in Special Collections and cataloged. All catalog records contain a "Gift of Grace Cavalieri" note.
Books with testimonial by Grace Cavalieri
Frequently Grace Cavalieri writes testimonials or short reviews on the back cover of poetry books. These books are not retained in the collection. A list of some of those is below.
Final Deployment by Ann Quinn
Starlight & Error by Remica Bingham-Risher
Carousel new & selected poetry & fiction by Judith R. Robinson
The Bloomsberries and other curiosities poems by Lauri Byro
Trump Sonnets Volume 2 by Ken Waldman
Horse and Iron selected poems by Gred Kuzma
Crossing places by Ernestine Cowalton
The Book of Donuts edited by Jason Lee Brown and Shanie Latham
Poetry; Photographs; Washington (D.C.); DVDs; Plays (document genre); Audiocassettes; Color slides; Digital audio tapes; Videocassettes; Walker, Alice; Wilbur, Richard; Nemerov, Howard; Strand, Mark; Miller, E. Ethelbert; Miller, May; Jordan, June; Lorde, Audre; Clifton, Lucille; Ginsberg, Allen; Atwood, Margaret; Brooks, Gwendolyn
- Magnetic audiotape reels, 1976-1985; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically according to the program title, and then chronologically. Additional recordings of plays, poetry readings, and collaborative works by Cavalieri, as well as those reels that list only the author's name or a single broadcast of a radio program, are collected under the title "Miscellaneous Recordings." Reels within the "Miscellaneous Recordings" section are arranged chronologically if dated. If undated, reels are arranged alphabetically by the author's name.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists magnetic audiotape reels, the bulk of which were recorded between 1976 and 1980; there are also many undated reels. Reels that record a single program appear in the container list alphabetically according to the program title, and then chronologically. The series includes the radio programs "Poetry from the City," "The Poet and the Poem," and "Expressions." Additional recordings of plays, poetry readings, and collaborative works by Cavalieri, as well as those reels that list only the author's name or a single broadcast of a radio program, are collected under the title "Miscellaneous Recordings." Reels within the "Miscellaneous Recordings" section are arranged chronologically if dated. If undated, reels are arranged alphabetically by the author's name.
  - "Poetry From the City: Ascension Marathon 1976; Tracey Connolly and Janet Haley." (Box 17A, Reel 301)
  - "Poetry from the City: William Claire and Stuart Friebert.", 09/30/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 302)
    General note
    Note: "Sunday Jan. 23. Poetry from the City. Folger Shakespeare Library. William Claire and Stuart Friebert. First readings of season for "Midday Muse". Introductions by acclaimed poet Linda Pastan. Bill Claire was founder of Voyages Magazine. His reading includes the premiere of a new poem about life as a schoolboy in a poem which is definitive and exciting. Stuart is on the faculty of Oberlin College and Co- Editor of Field Magazine. His poems are compassionate and strong. This is a combination of two highly cultivated writers.
  - "Poetry from the City: William Claire and Stuart Friebert.", 09/30/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 303)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Beth Joselow, Harrison Fisher, Patricia Garfinkel.", 10/07/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 304)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Beth Joselow, Harrison Fisher, Patricia Garfinkel.", 10/07/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 305)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Beth Joselow, Harrison Fisher, Patricia Garfinkel.", 10/07/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 306)
  - "Poetry from the City: Alan Austin and Myra Sklarew.", 10/12/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 307)
  - "Poetry from the City: Alan Austin and Myra Sklarew.", 10/12/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 308)
  - "Poetry from the City: Shirley Kaufman.", 10/14/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 309)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folger Library; Marge Piercy.", 10/20/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 310)
    Note: "Sat Dec. 26. The joint is jumping at the Folger. If Shakespeare is paternalistic, there was no room for the poor guy this night. Every woman poet, or woman poet seemed to be on hand to hear this reading by a woman who has transcended poetry to become a cultural heroine in the new society. Introduction by the venerable Poet, Robert Hayden. The poetry sounds stronger than ever. The writing is brilliant and the reading rich and im-passioned. The poem about rape will stay as a social document on our age."
  - "Poetry from the City: Reed Whittemore.", 10/26/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 311)
    Note: "Reed Whittemore: Consultant in poetry at Library of Congress 1963-64, professor of English at UMD (from 1968 to pres [1976]), literary editor of New Republic (1969-73); most recent work "The Poetess- Journalist Works at the New Republic". Themes of Poems: 1) about his youngest child; 2) about being in the hospital (Song of the Patient Patient); 3) about a poet's diary; what happens in the Howard Johnson restaurant; 5) super-market poem of love. Everyday subjects with bits of unique sarcasm. Witty everyday themes with streaks of sarcasm that makes the poem a poignant piece of social comment."
  - "Poetry from the City: Reed Whittemore.", 10/26/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 312)
  - "Poetry from the City: Joan Retallack.", 10/28/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 313)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folio Bookstore; Jane Delynn and Ed Cox.", 10/30/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 314)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folio Bookstore; Jane Delynn and Ed Cox.", 10/30/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 315)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; David McAleavey and Marilyn Hacker.", 11/04/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 316)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; David McAleavey and Marilyn Hacker.", 11/04/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 317)
  - "Poetry from the City: James Merrill.", 11/08/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 318)
  - "Poetry from the City: James Merrill.", 11/08/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 319)
  - "Poetry from the City: Ruth Whitman and John Lievsay.", 11/11/1976 (Box 17A, Reel 320)
    Note: "Poetry from the City, Nov 11 at the Folger Library session called Midday Muse. Poets introduced by David McAleavey of George Washington University. The Folger Library presents Poetry from the City with the witty and amusing John Lievsay and the sensitive personal Ruth Whitman. Ruth Whitman's poetry is lyrical and romantic. She deals more with emotions and feelings rather than outside facts. One of her poems protested the Jewish Women having to cut their hair off when married-- protesting women's role in society. Her others were funny in a way, but mostly romantic and one sad and reflective--(sure use that word a lot but when you sit and think about something isn't it reflecting (how about contemplative?). Her last was a love poem. All of her poems are sensitive and somehow quiet. She was awfully good. John Lievsay is an elderly poet--his poems are very witty--he sounds very wise and intelligent--most of them rhyme all the way through--but they are enjoyable to listen to.
  - "Poetry from the City: Ruth Whitman and John Lievsay.", 11/11/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 321)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folio Books [poets not listed].", 11/12/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 322)
  - "Poetry from the City: Washington Women's Arts Center; Janet Newman.", 11/12/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 323)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Hispanic American Poets Gloria Mercedes Anthony, Magdelena Flores, Mara Lyon reciting the poetry of Perez Gomez.", 11/16/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 324)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Hispanic American Poets Gloria Mercedes Anthony, Magdelena Flores, Mara Lyon reciting the poetry of Perez Gomez.", 11/16/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 325)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folger Library; Heddy Reid and Harriet Zinnes.", 11/18/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 326)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folger Library; Heddy Reid and Harriet Zinnes.", 11/18/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 327)
  - "Poetry from the City: Bethesda Library; Grace Cavalieri and Dan Johnson., 11/23/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 328)
  - "Poetry from the City: Bethesda Library; Grace Cavalieri and Dan Johnson., 11/23/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 329)
  - "Poetry from the City: Gabrielle Edgcomb and Gregory Millard.", 12/09/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 330)
  - "Poetry from the City: Washington Projects for the Arts Ascension 21 Marathon.", 12/21/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 331)
  - "Poetry from the City: Washington Projects for the Arts Ascension 21 Marathon.", 12/21/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 332)
  - "Poetry from the City: Washington Projects for the Arts Ascension 21 Marathon.", 12/21/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 333)
  - "Poetry from the City: Washington Projects for the Arts Ascension 21 Marathon.", 12/21/1976 (Box 18A, Reel 334)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folger Library; Henry Taylor and John Eagles.", 01/03/1977 (Box 18A, Reel 335)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folger Library; Henry Taylor and John Eagles.", 01/03/1977 (Box 18A, Reel 336)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folger Library; Henry Taylor and John Eagles.", 01/03/1977 (Box 18A, Reel 337)
  - "Poetry from the City: Bookworks; Lynne Dreyer, Mark Strand.", 01/30/1977 (Box 18A, Reel 338)
  - "Poetry from the City: Bookworks; Lynne Dreyer, Mark Strand.", 01/30/1977 (Box 18A, Reel 339)
  - "Poetry from the City: Ascension #24; James Coleman, Denise Oliver.", 02/25/1977 (Box 18A, Reel 340)
    Notes: "Denise Oliver, Ascension 24. James Coleman. Original, uses [unreadable], innovative, poetry, philosophy, god-Karma, Religious, love poems, semi romantic.
  - "Poetry from the City: Ascension #24; James Coleman, Denise Oliver.", 02/25/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 341)
  - "Poetry from the City: Ascension #24; James Coleman, Denise Oliver.", 02/25/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 342)
  - "Poetry from the City: Maya Gallery, Summer 1977, Gaston Neal; George Washington University, 03/01/77, Audre Lorde." (Box 19A, Reel 343)
  - "Poetry from the City: Maya Gallery, Summer 1977, Gaston Neal; George Washington University, 03/01/77, Audre Lorde." (Box 19A, Reel 344)
  - "Poetry from the City: Allen Ginsberg.", 03/07/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 345)
    Notes: "[Part one:] His poetry is a little unusual (original)in that he uses music to accompany it, if only one instrument for rhythms. He used one rhythmic instrument in one of his poems. His poems in themselves have a musical, or rhythmic sound to them in and of themselves. Most of the subjects of the poems are about the C.I.A. involved with drug traffic in IndoChina (Saigon and Cambodia). His tone is both cynical and a little angry even as it's comical. But it is in no way really happy. His last poem [on the first reel] showed the difference between American cities and those in Saigon, Cambodia and Indochina, people, atmosphere, environment. His poems are interesting and musical, using poetry to convey information and protest. [Part two:] Same type with organ music accompanying it. Sounded a bit like a spiritual in style but not words. (Some of it was distorted so I couldn't really understand the words. The organ distorted everything.) This is not politically oriented at all--these are more close to home. A little dramatic, like an actor. About Age, family. Tone is sort of a soft mellow sound instead of the protest poems. Perhaps still sort of cynical or sad. Songs about age death are the themes of these poems. (Like I said he's not a happy poet). He varies between songs and just plain poetry throughout the tape. Toward the end, his songs become more cheerful. But I believe the main tone of the poetry was reflective, somewhat cynical poetry that conveys one or two different messages."
  - "Poetry from the City: Allen Ginsberg.", 03/07/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 346)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Carolyn Kizer and Randolph von Abele.", 04/14/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 347)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Carolyn Kizer and Randolph von Abele.", 04/14/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 348)
  - "Poetry from the City: Howard University; Alice Walker.", 1977 (Box 19A, Reel 349)
  - "Poetry from the City: Howard University; Alice Walker.", 1977 (Box 19A, Reel 350)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Greg Hannan, Dan Johnson, Anne Leftner.", 05/12/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 351)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Greg Hannan, Dan Johnson, Anne Leftner.", 05/12/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 352)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Greg Hannan, Dan Johnson, Anne Leftner.", 05/12/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 353)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; E. Ethelbert Miller, June Jordan.", 06/02/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 354)
  - "Poetry from the City: Maya Gallery; Greg Tate.", 1977 (Box 19A, Reel 355)
  - "Poetry from the City: Kennie Holiday reads Frank Ruffin's poetry (Onaje).", 07/03/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 356)
  - "Poetry from the City: Howard University Afro-American Studies Dept.; Amma Khalil and Ken Forde.", 09/19/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 357)
    Note: "The following program may contain language that some listeners may find offensive. If you feel you will be offended, please tune back in about an hour. Intro: This is Gwen Holland at Howard University bringing you "Poetry from the City" for WPFW Pacifica Washington."
  - "Poetry from the City: Howard University Afro-American Studies Dept.; Amma Khalil and Ken Forde.", 09/19/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 358)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folger Shakespeare Library; Thulani Davis and Ntozake Shange.", 10/10/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 359)
  - "Poetry from the City: Folger Shakespeare Library; Thulani Davis and Ntozake Shange.", 10/10/1977 (Box 19A, Reel 360)
  - "Poetry from the City: Maya Gallery; Sheila Crider, Michael Harris, Magham Keita.", 11/03/1977 (Box 20A, Reel 361)
  - "Poetry from the City: Maya Gallery; Sheila Crider, Michael Harris, Magham Keita.", 11/03/1977 (Box 20A, Reel 362)
  - "Poetry from the City: Maya Gallery; Sheila Crider, Michael Harris, Magham Keita.", 11/03/1977 (Box 20A, Reel 363)
  - "Poetry from the City: M.L.K. Library; Leon Damas Special, Readings by Jessica Tarahata Hagedorn.", 11/10/1977 (Box 20A, Reel 364)